Hello, and welcome to Lesson 33 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
您好 欢迎来到 Wolfram U 的微积分入门课程第 33 课
The topic for this lesson is exponential functions.
本节课的主题是指数函数
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
让我们从本课的简单概览开始
In the past, we have talked about polynomials
在之前的课程中 我们已经学习了多项式
and other kinds of functions.
与其他各类函数
For example, over here the function f is a polynomial function,
例如 函数f是一个多项式函数
the function g is a rational function,
函数g是一个有理函数
the function h is an algebraic function
函数h是一个代数函数
and the function p is a trigonometric function.
而函数p是一个三角函数
Here are the plots of these functions.
下面是这些函数的对应图像
In this lesson, we’ll go a step forward
这节课 我们将进行更深入的学习
and talk about so-called exponential functions.
我们会谈及所谓的指数函数
Let’s begin with a definition.
先说说定义吧
An exponential function is a function with the form a^x
指数函数是形式为a^x的函数
where a is a non-negative value.
其中a为非负值
Of course what that means depends upon what that x is.
当然 这个函数的意义取决于x是什么
If x is a positive integer, then all you do is
如果x是一个正整数 那么你要做的就是
you multiply the number a by itself x times.
将数字a乘以自身x的倍数
Here’s 3^4, and that’s just 81.
如计算3^4 就会得到81
But if x is a negative integer, then you take a reciprocal.
但如果x是一个负整数 那么就取倒数
In this case, you have 3^–4, giving you 1/81.
在这种情况下 计算3^-4 会得到1/81
Finally if x is 0, then a^0 is just 1.
最后 如果x是0 那么a^0就是1
Of course, we can go beyond that.
当然 我们可以走得更远一些
If x is a fraction like p/q, then you can either take
如果x是像p/q这样的分数 那么可以取
a pth power and then a qth root or the other way around,
p次幂 然后取第q个根 计算顺序不影响结果
and in the Wolfram Language, we have the Surd function
而在Wolfram语言中 我们有Surd函数
which does that nicely for you.
这对你来说非常有帮助
The main point is that these exponential functions grow very fast.
值得注意的是 这些指数函数增长非常快
In fact, they grow faster than any polynomial function.
事实上 它们的增长速度比任何多项式函数都快
Here are some plots of these functions.
下面是这些函数的一些图像
If a is greater than 1 like 3^x,
如果a大于1 例如3^x
then you have a very rapidly growing function.
那么你会得到一个快速增长的函数
But if a is between 0 and 1,
但如果a在0和1之间
then the function is a decreasing function.
那么这个函数就是一个递减函数
Of course if a is 1, then you only have a constant function.
当然如果a为1 那么就只是一个常数函数
So increasing, decreasing, constant.
以上即指数函数的增减性
The next point is there are several laws of exponents.
下一个内容是指数的几个规律
If you have a^(x + y), then that’s the same as a^x * a^y.
如果函数的形式为a^(x+y) 此算式可以转换为a^x*a^y
If you have a difference like a^(x – y),
如果算式的形式出现了差异 形如a^(x-y)
then you simply divide to get (a^x)/(a^y).
那么你只需通过除法处理算式得到(a^x)/(a^y)
If you have (a^x)^y, then you simply multiply the exponents
如果算式的形式为(a^x)^y 那么你只需将指数相乘
and you get a^(x * y) like over here.
然后你会得到a^(x*y) 正如这里显示的
Finally if you have (a * b)^x,
最后 如果算式的形式为(a*b)^x
that’s the same as a^x * b^x like over here.
其处理方式和a^x*b^x一样 如此所示
Okay. Now let’s talk a little bit about some deeper properties.
好的 现在让我们谈一些更深层次的属性
First of all, the exponential function is always continuous,
首先 指数函数总是连续的
which means that there are no breaks in its graph.
这意味着其图像中没有断裂
The domain of the function is all real numbers,
指数函数的定义域是全体实数
and the range is from 0 to ∞.
且值域是0到∞
But of course what happens to the function
当然 让一个指数函数
when you approach infinity depends upon the value of a.
接近无穷大时的极限 取决于a的值
If a is greater than 1, then as you approach ∞,
如果a大于1 那么当你接近∞时
you get an infinite value.
你会得到无穷大
As you approach –∞, you get 0.
当你接近-∞时 你会得到0
Just the opposite happens if you have a number a between 0 and 1.
如果指数a介于0和1之间 情况正好相反
Now when you approach ∞, you get a 0;
当你接近∞时 你会得到0
when you approach –∞, you get ∞.
当接近-∞时 得到∞
Okay. On to the derivatives of these functions.
好 现在来说说指数函数的导数
The point is that the derivative of a^x
需要注意的是 a^x的导数
is not x * a^(x – 1) as you might think,
和你所想象的的x * a^(x - 1)不同
but in fact it is a^x * Log[a].
实际结果是a^x*Log[a]
Here’s the derivative from D.
这是通过函数 D 得到的导数
Now the question is in which case does this logarithm term become 1?
那么 什么时候这个对数式等于1？
That happens when the number a has got a special value called e,
当数字a是一个叫做e的特殊值时 就会发生这种情况
and this e is named in honor of
这个名字 是为了纪念
the great Swiss mathematician Leonhard Euler.
瑞士的伟大数学家 莱昂哈德·欧拉
If you solve Log[x] = 1 with the Solve function,
如果你使用 Solve 函数求解 Log[x]=1
you get back that x is actually e.
这个根实际上就是e
In the Wolfram Language, we use E for the number
在Wolfram语言中 我们用E来表示这个数字
and use Exp to represent the exponential function
并用 Exp 表示指数函数
whose derivative is e^x.
这个函数的导数为e^x
The point is that this is the one function whose derivative is itself.
关键在于 这是一个“导数就是本身”的函数
You just get back e^x when you try and differentiate it.
当你试图对它求导时 你又得到了e^x
Of course if you’ve got something more complicated like over here,
当然 如果你有像这样更复杂的东西
then you can use the chain rule and get back the answer.
那么可以使用链式规则来得到答案
How about integrals?
那么积分如何？
Well, the integral of e^x is, again, e^x, plus of course the C.
嗯 e^x的积分还是是e^x 当然还要加上积分常数 C
But if you have a more general exponential function a^x,
但如果有更一般的指数函数a^x
then you get back a^x/Log[a].
那么得到的是a^x/Log[a]
Okay. Let’s go a step deeper into the number e.
好 让我们进一步了解这个数字 e
There are many ways to define e.
许多方法都可以定义e
The simplest one is of course to just say that
最简单的定义说
e is a number for which the Log[x] = 1,
e是Log[x]=1的解
but you can also define it using limits.
不过 你也可以使用极限来定义它
This limit over here becomes 1 when x is e.
当x是e时 这里的极限才趋向于 1
So does the other limit over here, which really is the sequence limit.
这里 另一个极限也是如此 实际上这是个数列极限
n is a natural number, so when n becomes very large,
n是自然数 所以当n变得非常大时
then ((1 + 1)/n)^n becomes e.
((1+1)/n)^n就变成e
Also, the area under the curve 1/x from 1 to a
此外 注意曲线1/x从1到a的曲线下面积
becomes 1 when a is the number e.
当a是数字e时 此面积才为1
Finally, you should know that
最后 你也应该明白
the approximate value of e is about 2.71828.
e的近似值约为2.71828
That’s a very important approximation
这是一个非常重要的近似值
well worth memorizing.
因而值得记住
The number e is really, really important
数字e真的非常非常重要
in mathematics, science and engineering,
无论在数学、科学或是工程领域
and you will come across it all the time
当你试图将数学应用于实际情况时
when you try and apply mathematics to practical situations.
你总能看见这个数字
As examples of where it occurs,
我们可以考虑一些实际应用
we can talk about exponential growth or decay.
比如人们常常谈到的 指数增长或衰减
Now, for example, you’ve got bacteria,
比如说 细菌就是很好的例子
and initially there are 10 bacteria,
假设最初细菌的数量是10
and then they double every hour.
并且这数量每小时就翻一番
That’s the law of growth.
这就是成长的规律
That’s the initial number.
这是最初的数字
That’s the growth rate.
这就是增长率
Here’s a plot showing that we actually have
这里有一张图 显示实际情况
exponential growth in this case.
这个例子中 实际情况是指数式增长
But on the other hand, if you have a radioactive material,
但另一方面 如果换做放射性物质
then you begin with some quantity like over here, and the quantity,
然后 你开始有一定的数量 比如这里的这个数字 并且这个数量
let’s say, halves every time  period,
比方说 每个时间段减半
then you have radioactive decay.
这就是放射性衰变
There’s growth and there’s decay, and both of them can be modeled
有成长 也有衰减 这两种情况都能够
very nicely using exponential functions.
被指数函数模型很好地描述
To summarize, an exponential function is
概括地说 指数函数是指
a function is of the type a^x.
一个形如a^x的函数
If a is greater than 1, it’s increasing.
如果a大于1 则是增加
If a is less than 1, it is decreasing.
如果a小于1 则递减
Of course there are many laws of exponents
很显然 许多指数定律
which are useful in practice.
在实践中是有用的
Now in general, the derivative and integral
一般来说 导数和积分
for an exponential function are constant multiples of the function,
对于指数函数来说 是函数的常数倍
but the special number e has a property that e^x
但特殊数e有一个性质 即e^x
has got integral and derivative both equal e^x
它的积分和导数都等于e^x
plus of course the constant C for the integral.
当然积分时还要加上常数C
The number e is really useful in many different fields.
数字e在许多不同的领域很有用
For example, you can talk about exponential growth and decay,
例如谈论指数增长和衰减时
and you might want to use the number e
你可能会要用到e这个数字
or some other base for the exponential.
或者一些其他底数来描绘指数函数
In the next lesson we’ll talk about logarithmic functions,
下节课我们将会讲对数函数
but before that, do revise today’s lesson.
但在这之前 请先把今天的课程复习一下
It’s an important lesson.
这是一堂重要的课
Exponential functions are got all the time,
指数函数时时刻刻会出现
and you should know them really well.
而且你应该对它们了如指掌
I’ll stop over here. Thank you very much.
这节课到这就结束了 谢谢观看